<tool id="genmot" name="Motif generation">
  <description>Generates motifs from a set of functionally related
      CRMs</description>
  <version_command>imogene --version</version_command>
  <command python>genmot_comp.py -s $species -i $coord_file -w $width -t $Sg -x $extent -e $evolutionary -t $Ss1 -n $gennbmots </command>
  <inputs>
    <param name="species" type="select" label="Family of species to consider">
        <option value="droso">Drosophilae</option>
        <option value="eutherian">Eutherian</option>
    </param>
    <param name="width" size="4" type="integer" value="10" label="Width of the motifs">
        <help> Motifs represent the affinity of transcription factors for
            binding sites (BS).  Please indicate here the *width* of BSs in
            number of nucleotides (nts). Typical values range between 8 and 12
            nts.  Note that motifs of larger width can model motifs with
            a specific core of lower width and flanking nts with background
            frequencies (non-specific non-coding sequences). However, large
            motifs are more difficult to infer when containing many degenerate
            bases.</help>
    </param>
    <param name="extent" size="4" type="integer" value="20" label="Allowed shift of a binding site position in orthologous species">
        <help>In order to be robust to mistakes in the alignments,
                *Imogene* allows for local shifts of the binding sites
                in orthologous sequences.
              Considering the first base of a binding site in the reference
                species, an alignment will make it correspond to a position
                <em>p</em> in an orthologous genome. The algorithm will then
                search for binding sites in this orthologous species at
                positions <em>(p-s,p+w+s)</em>, where <em>s</em> is the shift
                indicated here and <em>w</em> is the width of the motif.</help>
    </param>
    <param name="evolutionary" type="select" label="Evolutionary model used for motif generation">
        <option value="1">Felsenstein</option>
        <option value="2">Halpern-Bruno</option>
        <help><p><em>Imogene</em> makes use of the evolution of binding sites
                to infer motifs. In order to function, <em>Imogene</em>
                consider the mutation rate of bases under selection thanks
                to an evolutionary model.</p>
              <p>Two models are currently supported by <em>Imogene</em> (see
                refs at the end of the page for a detailed description):
                <ul><li>Felsentein: this model is simple and runs faster</li>
                    <li>Halpern-Bruno: this model has a deeper theoretical
                        ground and better predicts the speed of evolution of
                        the motifs but takes more time to run.</li>
                </ul></p>
            </help>
    </param>
    <param name="Sg" size="4" type="float" value="11.0" label="Threshold used for motif generation">
        <help><p>The <em>threshold</em>, expressed in bits, corresponds to the
                level of specificity of a motif.  As an order of magnitude,
                a threshold equal to 10 corresponds approximatively to one
                binding site every 1000 bases on average in the whole genome.
                Since we use conservation to define motifs instances, this
                number is actually an upper bound. Common values, that give
                reasonable results are comprised between 10 and 13 bits.</p></help>
    </param>
    <param name="Ss1" size="4" type="float" value="8.0" label="Threshold used to scan training set sequences for display">
        <help><p>Note that this scanning threshold is only used for the final
                display and does not interviene in motifs generation. In
                particular, a lower threshold is useful to check for cryptic
                sites in the sequences. </p></help>
    </param>
    <param name="gennbmots" size="4" type="integer" value="5" label="Number of motifs to display at maximum (between 1 and 10)">
        <help><p>The algorithm output consists of many motifs on general.
                Although, they are all present in the text file output, they
                cannot all be displayed and shown on the input sequences. It is
                usually fine to consider between 5 et 10 motifs. </p></help>
    </param>
    <param format="bed" name="coord_file" type="data" label="Training set sequences coordinates"><help>Please use the "Get Data" tool in the menu to import bed files</help></param>
  </inputs>
  <outputs>
    <data format="html" name="outhtml" label="Genmot html" />
  </outputs>

  <help>
**What is it for?**

*Imogene* has two main purposes:

i.  it detects statistically overrepresented motifs, considering closely
    related genomes, in a set of training sequences. These sequences are
    generally selected for their biological relationships, *ie*
    cis-regulatory role.
ii. it predicts novel cis-regulatory sequences based on user-selected
    motifs at the whole genome scale.

Currently, *Imogene* supports two genome sets: mammals and drosophilae, but we
are open to integrating other sets if you feel interested.

-----

**Genomes**

Two families of genomes are currently supported by *Imogene*:

- *Drosophilae*: genomes are taken from the 12 genomes project
  (A. G. Clark, *et al*. Evolution of genes and genomes on the Drosophila
  phylogeny. *Nature*, 450(7167):203-218, Nov 2007.)
- *Eutherian*: genomes are taken from the ensembl project
  (http://www.ensembl.org/, folder epo_12_eutherian)

-----

**Source code**

The source code of *Imogene* is available on *github*:
https://github.com/hrouault/Imogene.

It contains the main source code, as well as a documentation and local
installation instructions.  An online manual can also be found here_.
Any trouble concerning its installation or bugs should be addressed on
*github*.

.. _here: http://hrouault.github.com/Imogene>
            
Please, feel free to contact us for any question concerning *Imogene*:
Herve Rouault herve.rouault@pasteur.fr_,
Marc Santolini marc.santolini@lps.ens.fr_.

.. _herve.rouault@pasteur.fr: herve.rouault@pasteur.fr
.. _marc.santolini@lps.ens.fr: marc.santolini@lps.ens.fr

-----

**References:**

Please cite

H. Rouault, M. Santolini, F. Schweisguth and V. Hakim
(2013), Imogene: identification of motifs and cis regulatory
modules underlying gene co-regulation, submitted.

or

H. Rouault, K. Mazouni, L. Couturier, V. Hakim and F. Schweisguth (2010),
Genome-wide identification of cis-regulatory motifs and modules underlying gene
coregulation using statistics and phylogeny. Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U.S.A.,
107:14615-14620.
  </help>

</tool>
